# HAIWEN DIAO

## Three-year Doctoral Candidate

Intelligent Image Analysis and Understanding (IIAU) Lab School of Information and Communication Engineering Dalian University of Technology (DUT) No.2 Linggong Road, Dalian City, China, 116024

Address: Email: diaohw@mail.dlut.edu.cn \diaohw@mail.dlut.edu.cn

#### Research Interests

My primary research interests are *Vision-and-Language*, *Transfer Learning* and *Multimodal Large Language Model*. Specifically, my research in the vision-and-language domain strives to build up an efficient system that entails recognizing visual-semantic perception and contextualizing fine-grained correspondence across modalities.

## Experience

## Beijing Academy of Artificial Intelligence, Beijing

Sep.2023 — Present

Research Internship

• Director: Dr. Xinlong Wang (Computer Vision Center)

## Hong Kong University of Science and Technology, Dalian

Jan.2023 — Aug.2023

Remote Cooperation

• Director: Dr. Long Chen (Computer Science and Engineering)

### Tencent AI Lab, Shenzhen

Jun.2020 - Mar.2021

2020 Tencent AI Lab Rhino-Bird Focused Research Program

• Director: Dr. Ying Zhang, Dr. Lin Ma (Computer Vision Center)

### Education

## Dalian University of Technology (DUT), Dalian

Sep. 2021 — Present

Ph.D. in Information and Communication Engineering

- Thesis: Parameter-efficient Transfer Learning, Multi-modal Large Language Model
- Director: Prof. Huchuan Lu

## Dalian University of Technology (DUT), Dalian

Sep. 2018 — Jun. 2021

M.E. in Information and Communication Engineering

- Thesis: Person Re-Identification, Vision-and-Language Domain
- Director: Prof. Huchuan Lu

## Dalian University of Technology (DUT), Dalian

Sep. 2014 — Jun. 2018

B.E. in Electronic Information Engineering

• GPA: Top3% (School of Information and Communication Engineering)

### Awards & Hornors

#### Awards

- Silver Award of the 9th China International College Students' 'Internet+' Ministry of Education, 2023 Innovation and Entrepreneurship Competition (Industrial Track) (Project Leader) (Top 120/421M)
- Excellence Award of 2020 Tencent AI Lab Rhino-Bird Focused Research Program (9/27) Tencent AI Lab. 2021

## Hornors

• Excellent Graduate of Dalian City (Bachelor's degree)

Dalian City, 2018
Dalian City, 2016

• Lingshui Scholarship (First Prize) (Top 5%)

CEL ...

• China National Scholarship (Top 1%)

Ministry of Education, 2015

• Awarded Learning Excellence Award (First Prize) (Top 5%)

DUT, 2015/16

#### **Publications**

#### Conference Publications .....

- UniPT: Universal Parallel Tuning for Transfer Learning with Efficient Parameter and Memory <u>Haiwen Diao</u>, Bo Wan, Ying Zhang, Xu Jia, Huchuan Lu ⋈, Long Chen IEEE/CVF Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR), 2024. [Code]
- Similarity Reasoning and Filtration for Image-Text Matching

  <u>Haiwen Diao</u>, Ying Zhang, Lin Ma, Huchuan Lu ⊠

  Association for the Advancement of Artificial Intelligence (AAAI), 2021. (google citations: 250+) [Code]

## Journal Publications

- Deep Boosting Learning: A Brand-new Cooperative Approach for Image-Text Matching <u>Haiwen Diao</u>, Ying Zhang, Shang Gao, Xiang Ruan, Huchuan Lu ⊠ IEEE Transactions on Image Processing (TIP), 2024. [Code]
- Plug-and-Play Regulators for Image-Text Matching

  <u>Haiwen Diao</u>, Ying Zhang, Wei Liu, Xiang Ruan, Huchuan Lu 

  IEEE Transactions on Image Processing (TIP), 2023. [Code]

## Preprints (Under Review)

- Unveiling Encoder-Free Vision-Language Models

  <u>Haiwen Diao</u>\*, Yufeng Cui\*, Xiaotong Li, Yueze Wang, Huchuan Lu ⋈, Xinlong Wang ⋈
  Under Review. [Code]
- SHERL: Synthesizing High Accuracy and Efficient Memory for Resource-Limited Transfer Learning Haiwen Diao, Bo Wan, Xu Jia, Yunzhi Zhuge, Ying Zhang, Huchuan Lu ⋈, Long Chen Under Review. [Code]
- GSSF: Generalized Structural Sparse Function for Deep Cross-modal Metric Learning Haiwen Diao, Ying Zhang, Shang Gao, Jiawen Zhu, Long Chen, Huchuan Lu ⊠ Under Review. [Code]
- DenseFusion-1M: Merging Vision Experts for Comprehensive Multimodal Perception Xiaotong Li\*, Fan Zhang\*, <u>Haiwen Diao</u>\*, Yueze Wang, Xinlong Wang, Lingyu Duan ⊠ Under Review. [Code]
- LLMs Can Evolve Continually on Modality for X-Modal Reasoning
  Jiazuo Yu, Haomiao Xiong, Lu Zhang ⋈, Haiwen Diao, Yunzhi Zhuge, Lanqing Hong, Dong Wang, Huchuan Lu,
  You He, Long Chen
  Under Review. [Code]
- MoTrans: Customized Motion Transfer with Text-driven Video Diffusion Models Xiaomin Li, Xu Jia ⋈, Qinghe Wang, Haiwen Diao, mengmeng Ge, Pengxiang Li, You He, Huchuan Lu Under Review. [Code]
- Exploring Dynamic Transformer for Efficient Object Tracking
  Jiawen Zhu, Xin Chen, <u>Haiwen Diao</u>, Shuai Li, Jun-Yan He, Chenyang Li, Bin Luo, Dong Wang, Huchuan Lu ⊠
  Under Review. [Code]

### Patents Declaration

1. An Image Retrieval Method and Related Device

Huchuan Lu, <u>Haiwen Diao</u>, Ying Zhang, Lin Ma CN111914113A, China, 2020.

### **Professional Services**

#### Journal Reviewer:

IEEE TPAMI, IEEE TIP

#### Conference Reviewer:

CVPR (2022 - 2024), ICCV (2023), ECCV (2022 - 2024), AAAI (2023 - 2024), ACMMM(2024)

### References

### • Prof. Huchuan Lu (Ph.D. Advisor)

School of Information and Communication Engineering

Dalian University of Technology (DLUT)

Dalian, Liaoning, 116024, China

Email: lhchuan@dlut.edu.cn

## • Dr. Lin Ma (Industrial Director)

Meituan AI Lab

Chaoyang, Beijing, 100102, China

Email: forest.linma@gmail.com

## • Dr. Xinlong Wang (Industrial Director)

Beijing Academy of Artificial Intelligence (BAAI)

Haidian, Beijing, 100871, China

Email: wangxinlong@baai.ac.cn

## • Dr. Ying Zhang (Industrial Director)

Tencent WeiXin Group (WXG)

Shenzhen, Guangdong 518000, China

Email: zydl0907@gmail.com

## • Asst. Prof. Long Chen (Remote Director)

Hong Kong University of Science and Technology (HKUST)

Clear Water Bay, Kowloon, Hong Kong, 999077, China

Email: longchen@cse.ust.hk